lsoft.com 2012-11-18

# L-Soft Privacy Policy

* * *

### Introduction

At L-Soft, we are committed to the protection of your privacy and personal data. As a subscriber of our email lists, visitor to our Website, or customer of our products and services, you decide what information to give us. Any information that you provide will be held securely and in accordance with the legal regulations of data protection and electronic communication.

In accordance with our corporate policy, L-Soft pledges that it will never release, sell or trade your personal information without your consent. An exception must be made if we are required to do so by law or in the unlikely event of a sale of the business or transfer of assets.

The information that we gather falls into two categories:

  * **Personally Identifiable Information:** Personally identifiable information is any kind of information about a specific user, including name, email address and company. L-Soft only collects personally identifiable information that you explicitly give us.
  * **Non-Personally Identifiable Information:** Non-personally identifiable information is any type of information collected in Web logs, including IP address, browser type, or the use of cookies. This information is only viewed in aggregate form and is not routinely tracked to an individual site visitor except in special cases, such as responding to Internet-based attacks.

Our privacy policies provide important disclosures and details regarding our usage of your information.

### Privacy Policy for Email Lists

L-Soft has always been a strong advocate of permission-based email list communication. Our email list management software LISTSERV® has supported the opt-in function since 1986. In 1993, LISTSERV became the first software to introduce double opt-in, now an industry standard for email list subscriptions, which requires subscribers to respond to an email confirmation before being subscribed to a list. LISTSERV was also the first software in the industry with a spam filter and built-in virus protection. Our products are designed to put users in control of their own personal information.

Note that this privacy policy only applies to L-Soft's corporate email lists. While we urge all LISTSERV customers to follow the best practices of email communication, L-Soft is not responsible for customers' privacy policies. It is up to the discretion of individual licensees of the software to determine what information they collect and how they process and store it.

L-Soft collects personally identifiable information to serve email list subscribers in the most effective and efficient manner possible:

  * **Opt-In:** If you sign up to receive L-Soft email announcements or newsletters, we will use the information that you give us to provide the service that you have requested. The personal information that you provide will only be held for as long as you remain subscribed to the email lists. L-Soft issues subscriptions and collects your personally identifiable information according to a double opt-in policy.
  * **Opt-Out:** All of L-Soft's corporate announcement list messages include an unsubscribe option at the end of the message. If you inform us that you wish to cancel a subscription, we will promptly remove you from our mailing list, and your personal details will be deleted from our records.
  * **Information Collected:** Information collected may include your full name, email address, country and other information depending on your preference for a specific service. L-Soft communications are in plain text or HTML format (with images). When you sign up to receive email from us, you can select either of them. If you select the HTML format, the email may include a one-pixel gif to determine whether or not readers viewed the email. This process does not leave any information on your computer, nor does it collect information from your computer.

L-Soft complies fully with the federal CAN-SPAM Act of 2003 and EU Directive 2002/58/CE on Privacy and Electronic Communications. For more detailed information on data protection regulations, please see the legal framework section.

### Privacy Policy for Website

As is standard practice on many Websites, L-Soft logs non-personally identifiable information about site visitors to analyze Website traffic. This information is not routinely tracked to individual site visitors. It is only viewed and analyzed in aggregate form except in special cases, such as responding to Internet-based attacks.

  * **IP Address:** An IP address is an identifier for a computer or device on a TCP/IP network. L-Soft logs IP addresses to analyze traffic and improve the content of the Website. L-Soft does not routinely track IP addresses to individual users. In special cases, such as responding to Internet-based attacks or troubleshooting customer or subscriber problems, logs for Web and other Internet services may be used to track the particular IP addresses that are involved in the incident.
  * **Cookie:** A cookie is a message given to a Web browser by a Web server. The message is sent back to the server each time the browser requests a page from the server. The main purpose of cookies is to identify users, and, in some cases, to prepare customized Web pages for them. The L-Soft Website uses cookies to remember user regional preferences. L-Soft also uses cookies on a permission basis by offering LISTSERV administrators, list owners and subscribers the possibility to store their passwords with the help of a cookie. L-Soft does not use cookies to track individual users.
  * **Web Forms:** Web forms are used on the L-Soft Website as a mechanism for site visitors to contact L-Soft. The Web forms collect information, including name, email address and company name. This information is only used to answer and follow up on the request and is not shared with any third party unless explicitly mentioned.

### Privacy Policy for Other Electronic Communication

  * **Purchases:** If you purchase an L-Soft product or service, L-Soft will require you to provide appropriate data to fulfill the legal requirements on commercial transactions.
  * **Inquiries and Support:** If you send an inquiry or support request by email to a specific contact at L-Soft, it may not always be possible for this contact to provide the information requested. In such circumstances, we may pass your inquiry to another recipient who can fulfill your information request.

### Contacting L-Soft

L-Soft welcomes your comments regarding these privacy statements. If you would like to know what L-Soft email lists you are subscribed to or to submit questions or comments, feel free to contact us at: [editor@lsoft.com](mailto:editor@lsoft.com). Your feedback will help us improve our service to our customers.

To reflect this feedback, we may occasionally amend this privacy policy; thus, we encourage you to periodically review this page for any updates on our commitment to protect your information and provide you with improved content on our Website.

### Legal Framework for Electronic Privacy

Further information about email communication and data protection legislation:

**1\. United States: CAN-SPAM Act of 2003**

The CAN-SPAM Act took effect on January 1, 2004. The law, which supersedes and pre-empts provisions of many state laws, is essentially an opt-out law as opposed to the opt-in B2C component in the European Union.

The CAN-SPAM Act:

  * Bans false or misleading header information, including the "From" and routing information of the email message
  * Prohibits deceptive subject lines that mislead the recipient about the contents of the email message
  * Requires that email messages contain an opt-out mechanism and that these opt-out requests be honored
  * Requires that commercial email be identified as an advertisement and include the sender's valid physical postal address

**2\. European Union: Directive 2002/58/CE (Directive on Privacy and Electronic Communications)**

The directive establishes an opt-in regime, which means that no direct marketing electronic mail can be legally sent to natural persons (B2C) without the express consent of the recipient, unless a pre-existing business or commercial relationship exists. Consent is, however, not mandated for marketing to legal entities (B2B).

The Directive 2002/58/CE:

  * Requires prior consent from the recipient before any email marketing messages can be sent to natural persons (B2C)
  * Bans disguised or misleading sender information, including the "From" and routing information of the email message
  * Requires that email messages contain an opt-out mechanism and that these opt-out requests be honored
  * Requires that email messages contain a valid return address

**3\. European Union: Further Information on EU Data Protection**

Directive 95/46/CE of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 October 1995 on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data

<http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31995L0046:EN:HTML>

Directive 97/66/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 December 1997 concerning the processing of personal data and the protection of privacy in the telecommunications sector

<http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31997L0066:EN:HTML>

EU Directive 2006/24/CE of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 March 2006 on the retention of data generated or processed in connection with the provision of publicly available electronic communications services or of public communications networks, amending Directive 2002/58/CE

[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/Notice.do?mode=dbl&lang=en&ihmlang=en&lng1=en,it  
&lng2=cs,da,de,el,en,es,et,fi,fr,hu,it,lt,lv,mt,nl,pl,pt,sk,sl,sv,&val=425159:cs&page= ](http://eur-lex.europa.eu/Notice.do?mode=dbl&lang=en&ihmlang=en&lng1=en,it&lng2=cs,da,de,el,en,es,et,fi,fr,hu,it,lt,lv,mt,nl,pl,pt,sk,sl,sv,&val=425159:cs&page=)

First Council Directive 68/151/EEC of 9 March 1968 on co-ordination of safeguards which, for the protection of the interests of members and others, are required by Member States of companies within the meaning of the second paragraph of Article 58 of the Treaty, with a view to making such safeguards equivalent throughout the Community

<http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31968L0151:EN:HTML>

Directive 2003/58/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council 15 July 2003 amending Council Directive 68/151/EEC, as regards disclosure requirements in respect of certain types of companies, which gives the public easier and faster access to information on companies

<http://europa.eu.int/eur-lex/pri/en/oj/dat/2003/l_221/l_22120030904en00130016.pdf>

* * *

LISTSERV is a registered trademark licensed to L-Soft international, Inc.  
All other trademarks, both marked and unmarked, are the property of their respective owners.  
See Guidelines for Proper Usage of the LISTSERV Trademark for more details.
